<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A summons to iudgement. Or a sermon appointed for the Crosse, but deliuered vpon occasion in the cathedrall church of S. Paul London the 6. day of Iune, 1613. beeing the first Sunday of Midsommer Terme. By Thomas Baughe, student of Christ-Church in Oxford.</title>
            <author>Baughe, Thomas, b. 1577 or 8.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1614</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 99 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 33 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A05759</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 1594</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S101085</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99836909</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99836909</idno>
            <idno type="VID">1204</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A05759)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 1204)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1475-1640 ; 826:09)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A summons to iudgement. Or a sermon appointed for the Crosse, but deliuered vpon occasion in the cathedrall church of S. Paul London the 6. day of Iune, 1613. beeing the first Sunday of Midsommer Terme. By Thomas Baughe, student of Christ-Church in Oxford.</title>
                  <author>Baughe, Thomas, b. 1577 or 8.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 59, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by G. Eld, for William Iones, and are to bee sold at his shop neere Holborne Conduit, at the signe of the Gunne,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1614.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>On Job XXI, 14.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:1204:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:1204:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SVMMONS TO IVDGEMENT.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>OR</hi> A SERMON APPOINTED FOR THE CROSSE, BVT DELIVE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vpon occaſion in the Cathedrall Church of S. Paul <hi>London: the</hi> 6. <hi>day of Iune,</hi> 1613. beeing the firſt Sunday of Mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſommer Terme.</p>
            <p>By THOMAS BAVGHE, ſtudent of Chriſt-Church in Oxford.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>HEB: 10.37.</bibl>
               <p>For yet a very little while, and he that ſhall come, will come, and will not tary.</p>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by G. ELD, for WILLIAM IONES, and are to bee ſold at his ſhop neere Holborne Conduit, <hi>at the Signe of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>unne.</hi> 1614.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:1204:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:1204:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT REVEREND FATHER IN GOD, IOHN LORD BISHOP OF LONDON, continuance of all grace, and peace by IESVS CHRIST.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right Reuerend Father in God,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>OV that from the firſt haue beene a Father to my ſtudies, and are now, by Gods moſt gracious bleſſing to our Church, ſet as a Father ouer it, ſuffer mee with fearefull boldnes, and hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ambition, to offer vp to your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, not any Lordly, but this meane and lowly preſent. For my Vniuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie, my Colledge, my place, my per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, my profeſſion, my liuing, and all, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyne, and enforce me to vow, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrate to your Lordſhip, if it were poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble,
<pb facs="tcp:1204:3"/> more then my all. And on what fai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer Obiect can the eies of Oxford, and the hearts of Chriſt Church be ſet, then vpon you, who are one of the great bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings of Oxford, &amp; the very ioy of Chriſt Church hearts. True it is, that being con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcious of my owne priuat meanneſſe, and euer moſt feareful &amp; timorous to appeare in publicke, I had purpoſed to haue laide aſide this Sermon, as I my ſelf lie, in obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uion &amp; obſcuritie. But ſince it hath been, once, and againe deſired, <hi>prodire in lucem,</hi> to ſee the light; &amp; that by ſome high and honorable perſonages, ſuch as are emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent both in place &amp; power, it was not in my power to conceale and keep in that, which their graue wiſedomes thought fit to goe abroad. And I might haue beene condemned of rudenes, ſhould I haue denied the world that, which, vnworthy though it be, yet men of ſuch worth iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged might profit the world. And now right Reuerend Father I ſhal euer eſteem it my greateſt happines, if this too ſoone
<pb facs="tcp:1204:3"/> and vntimely borne infant, which cries to you for ſuccour, may be accepted &amp; fauou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of you. For weak though it be in it ſelf, yet beeing armed with your powerfull name, it will thence gather and collect ſtrength. I muſt confeſſe, &amp; the world will finde, it is an <hi>Embrio,</hi> an imperfect and formeleſs iſſue, for I had not time, <hi>Lambere foetum,</hi> ſo much as to cloath and coate this though my firſt borne child: and therefore the more bare and naked that it is, ſo much the more it needs to bee couered vnder the wing of your gracious fauour.</p>
            <p>It was S. <hi>Pauls</hi> ſpeech, <hi>Quis idoneus?</hi> who is fit for theſe things? and I may ſay, <hi>Quî idoneus?</hi> how can I fit this liuing thing the Preſſe, that am preſſed, and almoſt op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed with a world of labour &amp; care. And yet I eſteeme all my labour but eaſe; and my yoke, were it heauier then it is, ſeemes but light, ſince I liue vnder your Lordſhip, who haue euer been, and (to your immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall honor) continue ſtill, <hi>vir laborum,</hi> a ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and heauenly laborer in the Lords vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard.
<pb facs="tcp:1204:4"/> Againe it cheares vp my ſpirits, and glads my heart, that I ſerue &amp; ſit at the feet of ſo godly a <hi>Gamaliel,</hi> as the learned, reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious, &amp; moſt ſtudious &amp; painfull Doctor, the reuerend Doctor <hi>Spencer;</hi> whoſe name as it is famous through the Church, ſo ſhal it euer be moſt deare &amp; pretious vnto mee. But I feare, <hi>in publica commoda pecco, Qui lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go ſermone moror tua tempora;</hi> therefore to conclude all, I pray from the ground of my heart, that your Lordſhip may long and long liue happy in our Church, and that our Church may ſtill be happy in you, and that you, and yours, and all your holy endeauours, may euer be bleſſed from aboue, by Ieſus Chriſt the ſole head of the Church.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Lordſhips de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>ed, and euer to be commanded in all Chriſtian obſer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>e, <hi>THO: BAVGHE.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:1204:4"/>
            <head>Quid faciam cum ſurrexerit ad iudicandum Deus? Et cum quaeſierit quid reſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>debo illi?</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>When God ſhall come vnto iudgement, what ſhall I doe? when he ſhall aske, what ſhall I anſwere him? <bibl>Iob. 31.14.</bibl>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE Apoſtle Saint <hi>Paul</hi> was rapt vp on a ſuddaine into Heauen. 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 12. and I (that am not wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy to name a Saint, or to be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led an Apoſtle,) am rapt vp on a ſuddaine vnto this place, which I euer reputed an earthly heauen; and that the rather, ſince the moſt ſplendent and glorious Sunnes of our kingdome ſhine here, and the moſt gratious Starres of our Land, nay of the world, are pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced in this Orbe.<note place="margin">2. Cor. 12.</note> And though Saint <hi>Paul</hi> in his viſion, knew not whether hee were in, or with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out his body, yet I that come now with my vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:1204:5"/> vnto you, know that I am in my bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, but in a weake, a bruſed, a broken body, yet well is it with me, if like, not a Lamp, but a ſmal candle, I conſume my ſelfe to enlighten others. For we reade, that, <hi>virtus Dei infirmitate perfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citur,</hi> the power of God is moſt ſtrongly ſeene in a weake man; and my hope &amp; confidence is, that the Spirit of the Lord, which quickens all bodies, &amp; all ſpirits, will cheere vp a decaying body, and animate my fainting Spirit.</p>
            <p>When the Diſciples were ſent to ſpeake be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Iudges, Chriſt bids them take no care, for, <hi>dabitur illa in horâ,</hi> a word of wiſedome ſhal be giuen them in that houre: and beeing I am to ſpeake before you (graue &amp; reuerend Iudges,) my prayer is, <hi>vt detur hac in hora,</hi> that a doore of vtterance may be opened, and a tongue of the learned may be giuen mee for this houre. And ſince I come haſtily before you, what fitter text, what apter meſſage can I bring, then a foreſight of the iudgement, which is ready to haſten, nay fall vpon vs all. Now that your graue wiſdomes are aſſembled, to exerciſe the iudgements of this Land, what better preſent, or preſident, could I haue for you, then a touch and ſtraine of that iudgement, which muſt come vppon all lands; that ſo, <hi>iudicium iudicia,</hi> the iudgement of God might direct the iudgements of men; <hi>Et iudex iudices,</hi> and your righteous iudge might aduiſe you to iudge righteouſly.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:1204:5"/>
            <p>When I was firſt ſent to this ſecond Nini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue, this great Citie, I came, not like <hi>Ionas</hi> with fortie dayes, and deſtruction; but I came like the Doue, <hi>cum oliuâ pacis,,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen.</note> with a branch of Peace and Oliue in my mouth; yet now my Maiſter Chriſt, that came with a whip into the Temple, hath ſent me, <hi>cum virgâ iudicii,</hi> with a rod of iudgement in my hand. When Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> ſpake of iudgment there was a <hi>ferè perſua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſit,</hi> one almoſt perſwaded to bee a Chriſtian, &amp; would to God this my denouncing of iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, might perſwade, not one, but all, not partly but fully, to be, not nominall, but reall Chriſtians; for God ponders, <hi>vias &amp; ſemitas,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prou.</note> the high, broad, and beaten waies of man, as al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo there by-waies and ſmalleſt paths: and in all our waies, <hi>nullum ignorat factum qui omnia fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cit,</hi> he ſees, and ſpies out the leaſt fault, who made euery thing without fault. That Sonne of God who is, <hi>principium ſine principio,</hi> the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning without beginning, will iudge all that hath been done from the beginning: Hee that is α, and ω, the beginning and the end,<note place="margin">Reuel.</note> will iudge all that haue liued from the beginning of the world vnto the end.</p>
            <p>The day of this life is the day of mortal man, but the day of iudgement is the day of the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing God: not but that all daies are his; but ſuch is his mercy, as that, though he ſhew mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie euery day, yet hee hath reſerued but
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:1204:6"/> one day for his iudgement; but that is a day of blacknes, and of wrath; inſomuch that the Prophet <hi>Malachy</hi> cries out,<note place="margin">Malac.</note> 
               <hi>Ecce dies domini,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold this is, with a witnes, the Lords day; it burnes like a furnace, and all the wicked are but as ſtubble. The powre of the Lord had her day in the Creation of the World, the mercy of God had her day in the Redemption of Man that little world: and the iuſtice of God muſt haue her day, in the iuſt puniſhment, of the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſt and wicked of this world: For, <hi>fulminabit e coelo,</hi> the Lord will thunder from heauen, and the higheſt will giue his voice. And if the thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and ratling of a cloud bee ſo terrible, what terrour ſhall there be, when hee ſhall thunder, that ſits aboue the clouds? the thunder doth but, <hi>eradicare turres,</hi> demoliſh towres, and root vp trees, but when God ſhall thunder out his iudgement, <hi>extirpabit homines,</hi> he will cruſh and caſt downe King, Prince, and people, that haue not made him their fortreſſe and their towre: The thunder doth but, <hi>quatere nebulas,</hi> make clouds flye like birds vp and downe the aire, but when GOD ſhall thunder out his iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <hi>quatiet conſcientias,</hi> hee will appale and aſtoniſh the hart and conſcience: yet ſhal there be then great difference betwixt a good and a guilty conſcience; for a good conſcience ſhall bee mooued, <hi>ſed vt folium,</hi> but as a leafe, with a little winde and breath of Gods diſpleaſure;
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:1204:6"/> but the guiltie-one ſhall be remoued, <hi>vt fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dament<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> terrae,</hi> as the foundations of the earth are ſhaken, with the full rigour of Gods wrath. For then as Saint <hi>Hierome</hi> hath it, <hi>terra tre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>met, mare mugiet,</hi> the earth ſhall quake, the ſea roare, the aire ring, the world burne, and all this All, become as a firebrand and bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning coale.</p>
            <p>And if, <hi>tota terra,</hi> the whole pillars of the earth muſt moue, <hi>quî glebam terrae,</hi> how then ſhould this moue man, who is but a clod of earth? if that, <hi>virtutes coeli,</hi> the powres of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen muſt tremble, what will befall thoſe minds, of mud and earth, that haue neuer minded hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen? if the Angels of God ſhall ſtand then at a gaze, how agaſt will the wicked ones bee, whoſe portion is with the Diuell and his An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels? <hi>Si ſoluantur coeli,</hi> if the Heauens muſt cleaue, and the elements be rent a ſunder, <hi>quid corda terrena;</hi> how will earthly hearts faile and breake, in this day of ſorrow, and of won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der? if the righteous ſhall ſcarſe bee ſaued, <hi>vbi impius,</hi> where will the wicked, and the ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner appeare? if iuſt <hi>Iob,</hi> but thinking of iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; come with his, <hi>Quid faciet,</hi> what ſhall he doe; alas then! <hi>Quid fiet,</hi> what ſhall be done to the vniuſt, whoſe bodies muſt boile, and whoſe ſoules muſt frie for it, when GOD ſhall come vnto iudgement?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>When God ſhall come vnto iudgement what
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:1204:7"/> ſhall</hi> I <hi>doe?</hi> This text of iudgement diuides it ſelfe, as the world ſhall bee diuided in the day of iudgement, <hi>in deum &amp; hominem,</hi> into the Maieſtie of God the iudge, and the miſerie of man that cannot ſtand out in the iudgement: So that here may be obſerued, firſt, <hi>a iudge,</hi> ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, <hi>people to be adiudged,</hi> and thirdly, a <hi>iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment:</hi> In the Iudge and iudgement, there bee theſe heads; firſt <hi>the time</hi> when; ſecondly, <hi>the perſon</hi> who; thirdly <hi>the manner how; non mittet, ſeà veniet,</hi> he will not ſend but come; fourthly, <hi>the end</hi> wherefore, to iudge; fiftly, <hi>the order by which, quaeret,</hi> he will ſift and ſcan, aske, and vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite: he wil make a priuy ſearch, a ſtrict inquiſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on into the works &amp; words, &amp; thoughts of men. In thoſe that muſt be iudged there is a double miſery: firſt they ſhal not know, <hi>Quid facere,</hi> what to do, for, <hi>quid faciant contra factorem?</hi> How ſhal they make their part good againſt their Maker? and ſecondly they ſhall not know, <hi>Quid reſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dere,</hi> what to ſay; for, <hi>Quae verba valeant aduerſus verbum,</hi> what word can they haue againſt him that hath the words of eternal life? againſt him that is the word &amp; the life? againſt him that is the life of the word, &amp; the word of life?</p>
            <p>Againe, for iudgement there is <hi>firſt</hi> a <hi>time;</hi> for, <hi>factor temporis &amp; qui natus tempore,</hi> He that created time, and that was borne for vs in the fulnes of time, wil iudge vs, for our not vſed, or abuſed time: and then, <hi>ô quae deſtructio!</hi> what
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:1204:7"/> ruine wil come, and how much would we giue, to redeeme a little time?</p>
            <p>Secondly, there is a perſon, God, and in him, <hi>ô quae perfectio,</hi> O what perfection! for the Che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rubins couer themſelues from his face, and Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>banus ſhaketh at his voice!</p>
            <p>Thirdly, hee ſhall not ſend his Deputie, his Legate, Embaſſador, Agent or Factor, but hee ſhall come in his owne perſon; and there, <hi>ô quae conſolatio!</hi> O what comfort will there be, when he ſhall come for vs, that went vp to ſend the comforter vnto vs!</p>
            <p>Fourthly, he ſhall come, <hi>non indicare,</hi> not to finger or point out our ſinne, <hi>ſed iudicare,</hi> but to iudge vs, for euery, euen the leaſt ſin; and here <hi>ôquae deſolatio!</hi> O what deſolation wil he work, on the wicked workers of the earth!</p>
            <p>Briefely, God, and not an Angell, or meere man; will come, and not ſend; to iudge, and not ſaue; and in iudgement, <hi>quaeret non teget,</hi> he will reueale, not conceale ſinnes; and then, <hi>Quid facient?</hi> when ſinners are vndone, what can they doe? <hi>Quid reſpondebunt?</hi> when the mouth of iniquitie &amp; wickednes ſhal be ſtop'd, what can the wicked ſay?</p>
            <div type="part">
               <p>But firſt of the time of iudgement. Some like forward Marchants, and bold aduenturers, haue preſumed to define and determine the terme and preciſe time of iudgement: of which ſome prefixe the yeare, ſaying it ſhall bee in
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:1204:8"/> the immediate end of the ſixe thouſand yeare; and there ground is this, becauſe a thouſand yeares are with the Lord as one day; whence they inferre, that as God made the world in ſix daies, ſo hee will deſtroy it in ſix thouſand yeares. Others out of the Prophet <hi>Malachy, Ecce dies domini;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Malac.</note> Behold the day of the Lord, auerr that God will come to Iudgement in the day. Others out of the Apoſtle, <hi>Veniet quaſi fur nocte,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">S. Matth.</note> Hee will come like a Theefe in the night; affirme that the Iudgement ſhall be in the night;<note place="margin">S. <hi>August.</hi>
                  </note> And Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> conſents thus farre to theſe, that it ſhall be, <hi>nocte rerum, non temporum,</hi> in a night and darknes of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and good liuing, not of ſeeing: Some go further and deſigne the very point &amp; moment of the night, for out of that of Saint <hi>Mathew, factus eſt clamor media nocte,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">S. Mat.</note> there was a cry in the midſt of the night, they collect, that God will iudge at midnight; and <hi>Caſsiodore</hi> hath the ſame building, though on another ground, for on that, <hi>percuſsit primogenita,</hi> God ſtrucke the firſt borne of Egypt at midnight, he concludes, that the iudgement ſhall bee in the middle of night.</p>
               <p>There bee yet ſome more fancifull and cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious then theſe, conceiting that the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſhall be in the fourth watch of the night, becauſe it muſt diſſolue the foure elements, and what was compacted or compoſed of the foure
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:1204:8"/> Elements. Others imagine that it ſhall be in the third watch, for that it is the worke not of the firſt, or ſecond perſon alone, but the ioynt worke of the bleſſed Trinity. Some deferre it to the ſecond watch of the night, for that the Sonne of God, the ſecond perſon in heauen, is appointed to bee the iudge of all the earth: and laſtly ſome tie it to the firſt watch of the night, becauſe it is ſaid, that <hi>Chriſt</hi> is the firſt fruites of them that ſleepe.</p>
               <p>Now to theſe vaine curioſities, and curious vanities, what haue we to oppoſe; namely firſt that of the ſcripture, <hi>Non nobis datum,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">S. Iohn.</note> it is not giuen vnto vs to know the times and ſeaſons, which God hath reſerued in his owne power: Secondly, of that day and howre knoweth no Man, no nor the Angels, no nor the Son,<note place="margin">S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi>
                  </note> but the father onely. Thirdly, as St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> hath it, <hi>Qui ante tempora,</hi> he that was before al time, and gaue beginning to time, will come to iudge vs in due time;<note place="margin">Reuel.</note> when that of the Reuela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſhall be true, <hi>Tempas not erit amplius,</hi> there ſhall bee no longer time.</p>
               <p>And heere me thinkes I may fitly gather one queſtion out of S. <hi>Auguſtine,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">S. <hi>August.</hi>
                  </note> for where he ſaith <hi>tam occultas dies iudieii, vt lateat ipſum tudicem,</hi> the day of iudgement is ſo ſecret and cloſe, that it is vnknowne euen to the iudge, it may ſeeme perhaps to ſome, not fully Orthodoxe and good; for what, hath the father committed
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:1204:9"/> 
                  <hi>iudicium filio,</hi> all iudgement to the Sonne, and yet retained, <hi>diem iudicii,</hi> the day of iudgement vnto himſelfe? I will not, either diſpute or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fine this poynt, onely I will poynt out, what o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers ſay.<note place="margin">S. <hi>Auguſt.</hi>
                  </note> Some affirme that the Sonne knowes not the day of iudgement, <hi>quà homo ſed quà Deus,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Bellar.</note> as hee is man, but as he is God: Others that hee knew it as man, but not to reueale it vnto men: others that he knew it not as a Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, <hi>qui tum erat,</hi> which he onely was while he was in the world;<note place="margin">S. <hi>Auguſt.</hi>
                  </note> but as a iudge, <hi>qui nondum e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat,</hi> which he is not till he ſhall come to iudge the world: <hi>Sed ſatis temporis in tempore,</hi> I haue ſpent time enough in bolting out the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment time, I will therefore conclude this point with ſome few moralls.<note place="margin">S. <hi>Greg.</hi>
                  </note> And firſt that of S. <hi>Gregory, Latet dies vltimus, vt omnes obſeruen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur dies,</hi> The laſt day is not ſpecified to man, that man might iudge euery day his laſt: <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly,</hi> that of S. <hi>Auguſtine,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">S. <hi>Auguſt.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>latet iudicium, ſed vniuerſale, non tuum; quia mors tua, iudicium tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um:</hi> The day of the generall iudgement thou canſt not find, but thy particular iudgement will find thee in the day of thy death. <hi>Thirdly</hi> that of the ſame <hi>S. Auguſtine,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">S <hi>Auguſt.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Latet iudicium, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men piorum fidem non latet, iuſtum eſſe vt lateret,</hi> The day of iudgement is obſcure, yet they that are enlightened by faith, ſee reaſon why it ſhould not ſee the light. Laſtly that of Saint <hi>Bernard,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">S. <hi>Bernard.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Incertus dies quo veniet, vt ſic viueres
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:1204:9"/> quaſi hodie veniret,</hi> the day of Chriſts com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming is vncertaine, becauſe it might learne thee ſo to liue, as if he would certainely come this preſent day: and then bleſſed is hee, that ſhall heare; <hi>Hodie mecum eris in paradiſo,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">S. Luke.</note> this day ſhalt thou bee with mee in Paradice; ſo I come from the time when, to the perſon who; <hi>when God.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p n="2">2 God might haue ſent forth his ſummons; haue commanded both by earthly and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly warrants; he might haue made both An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, and Saints, and the ſoules of iuſt men, as his apparitors, and officials to conuent vs to iudgement; but to ſhew his Maieſtie, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaſe his out of miſery, <hi>apparebit ipſe,</hi> God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe will appeare in iudgement: And if GOD come to be our iudge, then doubtleſs there will be, <hi>rectum iudicium,</hi> a right &amp; true iudgement;<note place="margin">Pſal.</note> for God is truth, &amp; he cannot faile; either <hi>igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantiâ iuris,</hi> as not knowing the law, for he gaue the law, &amp; will iudge, as S. <hi>Iohn</hi> intimates,<note place="margin">S. Iohn.</note> acor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to <hi>Moſes,</hi> and the law; nor yet <hi>ignorantiâ facti,</hi> as not ſeeing the fact, for hee knowes our <hi>thoughts</hi> long before, and therfore much more are our <hi>facts</hi> and <hi>deeds</hi> before him.</p>
               <p>Againe, if it be God that will iudge the earth, then ſure, <hi>aequum iudicium,</hi> his iudgement will be righteous and good; for, <hi>nec errat ipſe, nec ſuſtinet errantem,</hi> hee cannot ſinne him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, neither yet endure a wilfull ſinner;
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:1204:10"/> and we cannot corrupt him with preſents and goods, for, <hi>bonorum non indiget,</hi> as the Pſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſt<note place="margin">Pſal.</note> hath it, he hath no need of our goods: we cannot win him with perſonall fauour, for God is no accepter of perſons: and laſtly wee can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not moue him to malice or hate, for, <hi>nihil odit eorum quae fecit,</hi> the maker of all, hateth nothing that he did make.</p>
               <p>And here I muſt craue leaue to queſtion, and reſolue ſome doubts, <hi>Firſt, multi dicuntur Dii,</hi> ſince many be called <hi>Gods,</hi> in holy Writ, it may be queſtioned, which of thoſe gods ſhall bee our iudge: For the <hi>Angels</hi> they are called gods, GOD ſtood in the aſſemblie of gods, ſaith the Pſalme;<note place="margin">Pſal.</note> and yet the Angels ſhall not iudge vs, ſince Saint <hi>Paul</hi> tels vs, that wee ſhall iudge <hi>the Angels: Secondly,</hi> the <hi>diuels</hi> are called gods,<note place="margin">Pſal.</note> but the gods of the Gentiles, <hi>Dii genti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um Daemonia,</hi> the <hi>gods</hi> of the Gentiles are <hi>diuels;</hi> neither yet ſhall theſe bee our iudges, for the Prince of this world (that is the Diuell) is iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged already:<note place="margin">Pſal.</note> 
                  <hi>Thirdly,</hi> the <hi>iust</hi> and righteous men are called <hi>gods,</hi> I haue ſaid you are gods: and yet theſe ſhall not iudge vs, for, <hi>vix ſtabit iuſtus in iudicio,</hi> the iuſt ſhall ſcarſe ſtand out, nay vp, in iudgement. <hi>Fourthly,</hi> Kings are called gods, the gods of the earth are lifted vp; and yet though theſe be Kings in this world, they ſhall not be Iudges in another: but, as it is in the booke of Wiſedome,<note place="margin">Wiſedome.</note> 
                  <hi>Potentes potenter,</hi>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:1204:10"/> mighty Kings ſhal be mightily puniſhed, if they ſinne againſt the Almightie. <hi>Fiftly, Prieſts</hi> are called <hi>gods, offerte Dii,</hi> let the Prieſts offer, and yet theſe ſhall not iudge vs; for both Prieſt and people, <hi>congregetur coram Deo,</hi> muſt ſtand be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the tribunall of God. <hi>Sixtly, Magiſtrates</hi> are called gods, <hi>Diis ne detrahas,</hi> ſpeake not euill of the Magiſtrates, and yet nor they ſhall be our iudges, for they are but Gods ſtewards, vnder God, and muſt render, <hi>rationem villica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionis,</hi> an exact account of their Stewardſhips vnto God. <hi>Laſtly, Iudges</hi> they are called gods, the cauſe was brought, <hi>ad Deos,</hi> vnto the Iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, and yet though theſe execute the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of God vpon earth, God himſelfe ſhall come from heauen to iudge them. For, <hi>habent vel ſupremi iudices ſuperiorem iudicem,</hi> the Lord chiefe Iuſtices of this world, haue there Lord aboue, that ſhall doe them iuſtice: So then we muſt now, excluding al theſe, conclude all, <hi>Iudex vniuerſalis, deus vniuerſi,</hi> that hee that made all, will iudge all. Hee that is God will iudge the gods: hee that is the Angell of the great counſell, will iudge the Angels: hee that is a King, will iudge the Kings: hee that is a Prieſt, will iudge the Prieſts: <hi>Iudex iudices, homo homines, Chriſtus omnes iudicabit;</hi> Hee is Iudge, that will cenſure and ſentence Iudges: hee that is man, will conuent and conuict man; and yet there ſhall bee but one iudge of all
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:1204:11"/> men, euen IESVS CHRIST God and Man.</p>
               <p>Againe, ſince God ſhall iudge, and there be, though but one God, yet three perſons, it may be queſtioned, which of the three perſons ſhall be our Iudge? And this the Pſalmiſt ſeemes to anſwere,<note place="margin">Pſal.</note> when hee ſaith, <hi>Deus veſter veniet,</hi> Hee ſhall bee your Iudge that is moſt yours; Now the ſecond perſon is moſt ours; for hee was borne to vs, he liued with vs; hee died for vs; and what he either did or ſuffered, it was all for the good of vs.</p>
               <p>But why doth the ſecond perſon iudge and not the firſt?<note place="margin">S. Iohn</note> Why the Sonne and not the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther? <hi>Firſt,</hi> becauſe Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> tels vs, the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hath giuen all iudgement to the Sonne; and to the Sonne,<note place="margin">S. Bern.</note> as Saint <hi>Bernard</hi> expounds it, <hi>non quà filius ſuus, ſed hominis filius,</hi> not as hee is the Sonne of God begotten before the world, but as he is the Son of the bleſſed Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin, borne in the world; <hi>Secondly,</hi> the Son iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth, and not the Father, becauſe it beſt fitteth a King to iudge his owne Subiects; and we are now the immediate ſubiects of the Son: In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed in our Creation, wee were abſolutely the ſubiects of God; but by rebelling againſt God, wee became the ſlaues and vaſſals of Satan, and not the Subiects of our God; yet now beeing bought out of the ſubiection of Satan, by the precious bloud of the Sonne of God, wee become the ſubiects of the Sonne: Not
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:1204:11"/> that this is to be vnderſtood, <hi>excluſiue,</hi> as exclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding from the worke of our Redemption, the Father, or the Holy Ghoſt: <hi>Sed appretiatiue,</hi> as the Schoolemen ſpeake, but becauſe the price of our Redemption, was paide by the Sonne, and not the perſon of the Father, or ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt; and in that the Sonne did, <hi>ſuſtinere poenas,</hi> vndergoe our puniſhment, <hi>&amp; procu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rare praemia,</hi> and purchaſe our reward, he muſt, <hi>diſpenſare praemia &amp; poenas,</hi> both diſpoſe of our puniſhment and reward.</p>
               <p>Yet once more, ſince in the Sonne there is a double forme, a Diuine, an humane nature, it may bee queſtioned, in what forme, and na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture he ſhall iudge. Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> anſweres,<note place="margin">S. <hi>Auguſt.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>eâdem formâ iudicabit nos,</hi> Hee ſhall iudge vs in the ſame forme, wherein he ſtood before the iudge for vs; he ſhall iudge vs, not as God, but as Man: according to that of the Scripture, yee ſhall ſee, <hi>filium hominis,</hi> the Sonne, not of God, but of Man, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming in the clouds. <hi>Veniet qui deus, non quà deus,</hi> He that ſhall iudge vs is God, but he ſhal not iudg vs as he is God: not as he is God, becauſe, as <hi>Eſay</hi> hath it,<note place="margin">Eſay</note> 
                  <hi>tollatur impi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us,</hi> the wicked muſt be taken away, that he neuer ſee the glory of God; but as man, <hi>vt homines vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deant,</hi> that men may ſee, &amp; behold the iudge of men. The Papiſts ad, that not only the iudg ſhal be viſible, but out of that of the goſpel, they ſhal ſee, <hi>ſignum filii hominis,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">S. Matth.</note> the ſigne of the Son of
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:1204:12"/> Man, they would euict, that the croſſe ſhall come before him, as a verge, rodde, and ſcep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter vnto iudgement: but this opinion deſerues correction and a rod; for though with Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> we preach <hi>Chriſtum crucifixum,</hi> Chriſt cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifide vpon earth, yet I neuer finde, that the croſſe and crucifixe of Chriſt, was euer taken, as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> was, vp to Heauen.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Laſtly,</hi> ſince Chriſt ſhall Iudge vs as hee is Man, it may be queſtioned, whither there ſhall be no difference, betweene the man Chriſt li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing vpon earth, and the man Chriſt as hee ſhall come a Iudge from Heauen. Yes doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, much difference, not in ſubſtance, but in qualitie; for he that was here a man, <hi>natus praeſepio,</hi> borne in a ſtable, is there alſo a man, <hi>Sed regnans coelo,</hi> but commanding in the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens. Hee that was here, <hi>inter homines,</hi> a man amongſt men, is there, <hi>ſupra Angelos,</hi> a man aboue the Angels: Hee that was here, <hi>corpore infirmo,</hi> in a bodie of frailty, is there <hi>corpore glorioſo,</hi> in a bodie of glorie: He that was here, <hi>Salu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tor verus,</hi> a true Sauiour, is there, <hi>iudex ſeuerus,</hi> a ſharpe iudge: Hee that came here, <hi>pati pro dilectis,</hi> to ſuffer for his beloued, ſits there, <hi>triumphare cum electis,</hi> to triumph with his choſen and elect: he that came here, <hi>mori ad tempus,</hi> to die for a time, is there, <hi>deus vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens,</hi> liuing with God for euer; and the euerli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing God.</p>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:1204:12"/>
               <p>Yet (graue and Reuerend Iudges,) before I cloſe vp this point, I muſt ſay one thing that concernes you, that toucheth your ſcarlet, and your iudgement ſeates. For where it is ſaid, the Father hath giuen all iudgement to the Son, then, the Anabaptiſts inferre,<note place="margin">S. Iohn.</note> why then doe other the Sonnes of men iudge? and ſo learned Fathers of the Law, would they wound, nay ded you, who are the pillars of truth, the life of the liuing, and the defence of men appointed vnto death: But I anſwere, God hath giuen all iudgement to the Sonne, that is, <hi>omne futurum iudicium,</hi> all the generall, vniuerſall, and future iudgement: and <hi>ſecond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> for you, <hi>non tam vos, quam deus per vos iudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cat,</hi> it is not ſo much you, as God that iudgeth in, and by you; according to that of <hi>Deutero.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Deut.</note> you exerciſe the iudgements, not of man, but of God: and <hi>thirdly, Iudicat homo hominem in opere, ſed deus in corde,</hi> that though God onely iudge the heart, yet man may iudge, of the fact of man. And ſo I come to my third part, <hi>will come;</hi> when God ſhall come.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>In God riſing (for ſo reades the vulgate) and comming, (for ſo hath the Engliſh) vnto iudgement, I obſerue two things: <hi>First,</hi> the <hi>certaintie,</hi> then the <hi>vicinitie</hi> of the iudgement: It is not ſaid, <hi>Deus venit,</hi> God doth, or hath come, but, <hi>Deus veniet,</hi> God will come; and yet according to the rule of the Schoole,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:1204:13"/> 
                  <hi>Futurum in Deo aeque certum, quam aut praeſens aut praeteritum,</hi> that which is to come in God, is as ſure, as if it were either preſent, or paſt. And God wil come to iudgement both for the glorie of God, and of Man, and of Chriſt both God and Man: Firſt, for the glorie of God; for God hath promiſed a iudgement, and all the promiſes of God are yea, and Amen: The Prophets and the Apoſtles, both the Law, and the Goſpell beare witnes of a iudgement: I wil contend with thee in iudgement, ſaith God in <hi>Ieremie:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ier.</note> The Nations ſhall ſee my iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,<note place="margin">Ezek.</note> ſaith God in <hi>Ezekiel:</hi> I will ſit and iudge all people,<note place="margin">Ioel.</note> ſaith God in <hi>Ioel.</hi> In Saint <hi>Paul</hi> wee reade <hi>Statutum eſt,</hi> Death is appointed, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter it commeth the iudgement: And in Saint <hi>Peter</hi> wee finde a <hi>Iudicaturus eſt,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">S. Pet.</note> that, as if God had put on his robes, and were ſet on his iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſeate, hee is now ready to iudge the quicke and dead: God promiſed a floud and it came, <hi>Et qui verus diluu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o, cur non iudicio?</hi> hee that performed in the particular, ſhall he not alſo performe in a generall iudgement? In Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophie, <hi>poſito vno contrariorum,</hi> if we grant one contrarie, the other will follow: but wee haue had experience of Gods mercie, which is oppoſite to iudgement, and ſhall wee not alſo haue a triall and a iudgement? GOD hath ſhewed iuſtice in Heauen, on rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Angels, and will hee not ſhew iuſtice on
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:1204:13"/> men, if they rebell vpon earth?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> there muſt be a iudgement for the good of man: for here the holieſt and moſt heauenly men be in moſt heauineſs: <hi>Hic optimi peſsime agunt;</hi> here the righteous man hath moſt wrong; and therefore God will iudge, and do him right. Here <hi>Iezabel</hi> ſits brauing in a window, while <hi>Ieremie</hi> lies ſticking in the mudd. Here <hi>Diues</hi> ſits in his pallace,<note place="margin">S. Luke.</note> clothed richly, faring daintily, while <hi>Lazarus</hi> lies at his gate naked and hungry. Here <hi>Herod</hi> wil pleaſe his <hi>Herodias,</hi> though it be with the head of <hi>Iohn</hi> the Baptiſt; <hi>Nonne viſitabit,</hi> ſhall not God vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite, and come to iudgement for theſe things? Here the condition of the godly Chriſtian, is much like to the ſtate of Chriſt his maiſter, <hi>nec viuus domum, nec mortuus ſepulcrum habet,</hi> they haue ſcarſe a houſe wherein to liue, and (ſuch hath been the Popiſh furie) their bones haue not had reſt after their death: while they liued they found <hi>exilium, &amp; equuleum,</hi> baniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and the racke: and being dead, the wicked did, <hi>ſaeuire in manes,</hi> not let them reſt when they were at reſt:<note place="margin">Euſeb.</note> Much like to the ſtorie in <hi>Euſebi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us,</hi> where they were not content to burne the bodies of the Saints, but they caſt there aſhes vppon the water, with this obloquie, <hi>colligat Deus,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Reuel.</note> let the Lord gather them if hee will haue them. But O LORD, holy, and true, how long, how long? the bloud of thy
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:1204:14"/> Saints is ſhed round about this round world, and they are cut in peeces, euen as men cut and hew wood, and wilt thou not yet come, to be auenged on ſuch a people as this? Yes, ſaith the Pſalme,<note place="margin">Pſal.</note> the Lord will come, and not keepe ſilence: and, as it is in another Pſalme, Doubtleſſe there is a God that will iudge the earth.<note place="margin">Pſal.</note> And as in a balance, or a ſcale, that which is lighteſt mounteth higheſt, ſo thoſe that were of light, or no eſteeme in the world; ſhall then be taken vp vnto the higheſt: <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munt boni,</hi> though the godly, mourne here like a Doue, yet <hi>fruentur ſummo bono,</hi> then they ſhall be comforted, by that Spirit, who appeared in the likenes of a Doue: Though the good haue, <hi>preſſuram in terrâ,</hi> griefe, and oppreſsion vpon earth; yet they ſhall finde, <hi>vſuram in coelo,</hi> intereſt and increaſe of glorie in the Kingdome of heauen.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Laſtly,</hi> as there muſt be a iudgement for the glorie of God, and good of man: ſo it muſt alſo bee for the honour of Chriſt Ieſus, God and Man. For the world did not beleeue Chriſt to bee the Meſſias: the Iew held him but a meere, and miſerable man: the Gentiles derided him, as a crucified God; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore will hee call heauen, and earth, and come and iudge his people; and hee will come in ſuch power, and maieſtie, that the whole world ſhall confeſſe him a Meſſias; that the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:1204:14"/> Iew ſhall acknowledge him a God; and that both Iew and Gentile ſhall feare, and grieue, to ſee him ſo highly glorified, whom they baſely ſlew and crucified.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> I obſerued the neerenes and vici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie of the iudgement: It is not ſaid in the Apoſtles Creede, <hi>veniet,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Symbo. Apoſto.</note> 
                  <hi>ſea venturus eſt iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicare,</hi> hee will come, but hee is at hand, he hath, as it were, ſet forth, and is on his way comming to iudgement. <hi>Non inſtat iudiciam, ſed ferè extat,</hi> the day of iudgement is not ſo much future and to come, as it is already pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent and in ſight. <hi>Iudex adianuam,</hi> now is the iudge riding his circuite, now hath hee ſent forth his ſummons, now hath hee put on his robe, now is he ſet vpon his throne now is thy inditement reading, now is thy cauſe plead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and now, euen now, the ſentence of thy eternall life, or death, may bee paſſing: wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes that of the Apoſtle, <hi>Nunc eſt iudicium,</hi> hee doth not ſay, <hi>nunc erit,</hi> now the iudgement ſhall bee, as if it were comming, but <hi>nunc eſt,</hi> now is the iudgement of this world, as if this moment, this inſtant, and preſent now, were allotted for the iudgement. The world, that great man, hath the throwes and panges of death now ſeazing on him: And as man, the little world, when hee hath liued many yeares, draweth then neere vnto his end, ſo the world, that hath liued now almoſt ſix
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:1204:15"/> thouſand yeares, muſt needes conſume and haue an end: In the time of the Apoſtles the Kingdome of God was at hand, and now after ſo long a time as from the Apoſtles, is it yet farre off?</p>
               <p>When the Sunne hath paſſed the twelue ſignes,<note place="margin">Malac.</note> wee know then the yeare ends: Now Chriſt, our Sunne, hath paſſed through theſe ſignes, and therefore the yeare of the world muſt haue an end. Chriſt in his birth paſſed through <hi>Virgo,</hi> for hee was borne of a pure and bleſſed Virgin:<note place="margin">Inchino.</note> He paſſed <hi>Gemini,</hi> in his incarnation, for there was both a Diuine and humane Nature: Hee paſſed <hi>Cancer,</hi> in his deſcenſion, for hee deſcended, and came, as it were backe, from God to man. He paſſed <hi>Libra</hi> in his Paſſion, where his mercie, and his merits, ouer-wayed our miſery and ſinne: And (not to be, although I might bee, curi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous in all) hee paſſed <hi>Leo</hi> in his reſurrection, when hee roſe ſtrong as a Lyon, and ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came the graue, death, and hell, and that helliſh, roaring, and deuouring Lyon. Now then that Chriſt hath paſſed all theſe ſignes, it is a ſigne that the world, and all muſt paſſe away.</p>
               <p>Alas then why doe ſome, and ſome Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian men ſo liue, as if there were no iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment after this life? Nay more, as if they were Aduocates, and Orators, and Sophiſters for
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:1204:15"/> the Diuell, why doe they diſpute againſt the iudgement of our God? For ſay ſome, why ſhould God iudge man after his death, ſince hee hath his iudgement at his death? I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere,<note place="margin">S. <hi>Auguſt.</hi>
                  </note> that in death wee haue a particular iudgement, but God will alſo haue a generall: <hi>Secondly,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">S. Bern.</note> in death we haue the iudgement of the Soule, but God will iudge both Body, and Soule: <hi>Laſtly,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">S. <hi>Hiero.</hi>
                  </note> in death wee haue a ſecret doome, but God will haue an open aſſiſe, a publike Seſſions, and a manifeſt iudgement: O then put not farre from you the euill day, but ſo liue, as if you were to make, your perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall appearance before your God, this preſent day. For be you ſure, if any heare mee this day, and regard not in his heart the iudgment day, that euen this Text, theſe words, this Sermon of iudgement, will riſe vp againſt them in the day of iudgement. So I come to my fourth obſeruation, the end of Chriſts comming, it is to iudgement.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p n="4">4 And here I note theſe things: <hi>Firſt,</hi> the multiplicitie of iudgement<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> the qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie of Gods iudgement: <hi>Thirdly,</hi> the <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dromi</hi> and fore-runners of the iudgement: <hi>Laſtly,</hi> the followers and attendants on this iudgement.</p>
               <p>There is a manifold and various iudgement:<note place="margin">Bonauen.</note> For, (as <hi>Bonauenture</hi> notes) their is in God<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <hi>iudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cium praeſcienti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> a iudgement for thoſe ſinnes
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:1204:16"/> that were but intended: <hi>Secondly,</hi> there is, <hi>iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicium cauſae,</hi> a iudgment for the cauſe whence they ſprang, and the end wherevnto they ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded: <hi>Thirdly,</hi> there is, <hi>iudicium operationis,</hi> a iudgement for euerie euill act committed; And <hi>laſtly, iudicium approbationis,</hi> a iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of euery iuſt puniſhment inflicted. There is a iudgement of <hi>retribution</hi> for the good: a iudgement of <hi>reprobation</hi> for the euill: and a iudgement of <hi>diſcuſsion</hi> both for good and euill.</p>
               <p>There hath beene already a iudgement of <hi>water,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">S. Peter.</note> which did waſh away ſinners, but not ſinne: and there ſhall bee a iudgement of <hi>fire,</hi> which ſhall burne away both ſinne and ſinners.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> I noted the qualitie of Gods iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: and <hi>firſt,</hi> it is full of <hi>Maieſtie:</hi> for the King of heauen ſhall come, <hi>cum militia caele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſti,</hi> with all the armie, troupe, and traine of heauen: He ſhall ſend forth, as it were, his He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rald and Beedle, and call a Conuocation, of Angels, and Saints, heauen and earth, to cull, and ſeuer, and marke out his ſheepe from the goates. <hi>Poſuit thronum,</hi> God is come, as it were to the Kings Bench of his iuſtice; hee hath opened a booke, and another booke, as it is in the Reuelation,<note place="margin">Reuel.</note> to wit the booke, <hi>ſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiae diuinae,</hi> of diuine knowledge and ſcience, and a booke, <hi>humana conſcientiae,</hi> of mans guilty
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:1204:16"/> and accuſing conſcience. O wretched man, ſaith a good Father, <hi>tanta contra te fit praepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio,</hi> doth God ſo prepare, ſo muſter vp his men for thy iudgement, and wilt thou, either not feele thy imminent iudgement, or if thou feele it, not amend thy life, that thou maieſt eſcape in that fierie triall, and fierce iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment?</p>
               <p>If our gracious King, (whom the King of Kings ſet for euer as a ſignet vppon his right hand) ſhould take his Peeres, and Nobles, Biſhops, and Iudges, to iudge a rebell, or a malefactor, how would the countenance of that Traitor fall, his tongue faulter, his bodie tremble, and his heart and ſpirit euen thawe and melt away! And yet (good God) ſuch is our frailtie, that though we be traitors, to our iudge, our Sauior, and our own ſoules, yet we more awe &amp; feare, a <hi>temporall,</hi> then an <hi>eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall</hi> iudgement: and are more daunted with him that can but kill the bodie, and that for a time; then with him that can deſtroy both bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die and ſoule, and that for euer.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> there is mercie in this iudgement. For Chriſt will iudge vs, not by the letter and rigor of the Law, but as it were in a Court of Conſcience. <hi>Et Conſcientia qualis, ſententia ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis,</hi> and our verdict ſhall bee giuen in, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding and agreeing with the Conſcience wee haue within. Neither will our mercifull iudge
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:1204:17"/> proceed againſt vs without witneſſe; nay not without a thouſand witneſſes; and thoſe no forraine, aliene, or ſtrange witneſſes, but ſuch as are in our owne boſome; ſuch as are more inward with vs, then that ſoule which is within vs: For vnleſſe our conſcience, which is as the ſoule of the ſoule, doe like another <hi>Cerberus</hi> barke within vs, we ſhall eſcape that true <hi>Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berus</hi> and dog of hell.</p>
               <p>Beſides our mercifull iudge will not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne vs for one accuſer: for except <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Law accuſe vs,<note place="margin">S. Iohn.</note> as Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> hath it; except <hi>Singuli errores,</hi> our particular and ſingular er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors, ſingle vs out, and become, <hi>ſinguli accuſato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res,</hi> ech of them accuſers of vs; nay more, except man himſelfe doe condemne himſelfe, Chriſt who is God and Man, will not condemne. Nay more, except Sin and Satan come with plaine, direct, and vnauoidable euidence againſt vs, it ſhall yet, maugre all their malice, goe well with vs. And, Lord, how will that accuſer of his bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren in that day accuſe vs!<note place="margin">S. <hi>August.</hi>
                  </note> S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> brings him in thus inditing man, <hi>Iuſte iudex,</hi> marke, he doth not ſay, <hi>Bone Deus,</hi> good God, to mooue clemencie and mercie; but iuſt iudge, to whet and ſharpen him on to rigor and ſeueritie; and the bill of his enditement runnes thus, Indeed iuſt iudge theſe ſinners were thine <hi>per gratiam,</hi> by thy grace to them committed, but they are become mine, <hi>per culpam,</hi> by that ſin which they
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:1204:17"/> committed: They were thine, <hi>per miſericordiam</hi> in thy mercie; but they are become mine through their own miſery. They were thine, <hi>per paſsionem,</hi> through thy croſſe and paſſion; but they are become mine, <hi>per perſuaſionem,</hi> by my ſlie &amp; ſubtle perſwaſion. They were thine, <hi>crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione,</hi> in the creation; but they are become mine, <hi>deſtructione,</hi> ſince they haue brought themſelues to their deſtruction. They haue for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaken, <hi>Sacramenta tua,</hi> thy Sacraments, &amp; haue followed <hi>blandimenta mea</hi> my allurements, and therefore iuſt iudge, ſince they belong to mee, let them bee condemned with me. Alas good Chriſtians, being thus arraigned at the barr of Gods iuſtice, by whom will you bee tried? By your God? Why he muſt be iuſt: by a Iurie of Angels, and Saints? why they cannot quit you: For it is God that condemnes, and who can iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie? by your owne hearts? Why they cannot cleare you: What then remaines, but before we hold vp our hands at this barre, to cry guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie; And, Lord Ieſus, wee are guiltie of many, and manifold ſinnes, but remember ſweet Ieſus, that thy bloud was ſhed for ſinners. Wee haue committed that, <hi>quod damnet,</hi> which might ſend vs to a thouſand hels, but in thee there is ſuch ſtore of mercie, <hi>quae ſaluet,</hi> as may ſaue vs,<note place="margin">S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi>
                  </note> and ten thouſand worlds.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirdly,</hi> this iudgement is intolerable. For who can endure, when as aboue, our iudge is
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:1204:18"/> angry with vs; and belowe hell is gaping for vs: when within our vultur conſcience gnawes vs; and without the flame is ready for to burne vs: when on our right hand ſin oppreſſeth vs; and on the left the Diuel frights vs: When we haue God, and his Angels all againſt vs; &amp; none but deſperate men, and damned ſpirits with vs.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Laſtly,</hi> this iudgement is vnauoidable: for the hils cannot hide vs, nor mountaines couer vs from the preſence of the iudge: And whither can we fly from him, who is, not only here and there, but euery where? if we mount and ſoare vp to heauen he is there;<note place="margin">Pſal.</note> if we goe into hell, he is there too; if we take the wings of a Doue, and flye to the vtmoſt part of the earth, he is there: and if we lye downe in the deep &amp; bottomeleſs ſea, he is there alſo. If we ſay, peraduenture the night ſhall couer vs, we muſt know that the day and the night are to him alike. So that, <hi>pati in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tolerabile, &amp; latere impoſsibile,</hi> it is not poſſible to endure, nor poſsible to auoide the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirdly,</hi> I obſerued the precurrents, and fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runners of the iudgement: S. <hi>Gregorie</hi> notes that the laſt tribulation hath many antecedent troubles,<note place="margin">S. <hi>Greg.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>vt per crebra mala, caueantur aeterna ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la,</hi> that by the ſight and ſenſe of frequent euils, wee might eſcape the eternall euill. And <hi>firſt,</hi> the <hi>Sunne</hi> and <hi>Moone</hi> ſhall bee darkned: Now this may admit, either a <hi>litterall,</hi> or <hi>miſticall</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition:
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:1204:18"/> if we expreſſe it by the letter, then theſe viſible lights, the Sun &amp; Moone, ſhall bee darkned; yet not, (as ſome ſchoolemen hold,) <hi>priuatione luminis,</hi> as being depriued &amp; ſpoiled of their light, <hi>ſed ſuperveniente maiore lumine,</hi> but as being dimmed and ouerſhadowed with a greater light: And if wee runne from the letter to the ſpirit, then this Sunne is Chriſt, and the Moone is the Church of Chriſt; and both theſe haue been darkned; For Chriſt hath beene ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to be but a meere man; and the Church hath been dimmed, not by interpoſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of earth and land, but by ablation and taking away the Church land: and in this caſe may it not bee ſaid; <hi>non deletur peccatum, niſi reſtituitur ablatum,</hi> our ſins will hardly find remiſsion, if wee make no reſtitution. <hi>Pulcrum fuit,</hi> in the time of ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition it was thought the glory, and the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite of the Papiſt, to inrich, and endowe the church; yet herein their luxury did abound, &amp; they offend; but, (as the Moraliſt hath it,) it was on the ſafer part, being, <hi>in exceſsu,</hi> in making the church exceed in riches; and I wiſh that there <hi>Exceſſe</hi> doe not in the day of iudgement, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne the <hi>defect</hi> of them, who doe, <hi>non tondere,</hi> not onely fleece, <hi>ſed deglubere,</hi> but flea the church. S. <hi>Mathew</hi> hath eight ſignes that muſt,<note place="margin">S. Mat.</note> as it were, vſher in the iudgement. <hi>Firſt, many ſhall come in Christs name,</hi> ſaying; <hi>Ego Christus,</hi> I <hi>am Chriſt:</hi> and haue not, <hi>Batcabas,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Inchino.</note> and <hi>Tabicula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi>
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:1204:19"/> done this abroad; nay would this had not been done at home in this honorable Citie.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">S. Matth.</note>
                  <hi>Secondly, Nation ſhall riſe againſt nation:</hi> And is not this now true, almoſt in euery nation? for hath not the Turke riſen againſt the Chriſtian; yea and Chriſtians too againſt Chriſtians; but, ſweet Chriſt, from whence wee Chriſtians deriue our name, let it at length be thy will, that Chriſtians may ſhed no more Chriſtian bloud, but that all may iointly concur, to let the Turk bloud, and that euen in the heart veine.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">S. Matth.</note>
                  <hi>Thirdly, there ſhall be plague and famine, and they ſhall kill you.</hi> And, not to goe out of the gates of your Citie, haue not theſe things been found within your wals? Hath not the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Angell ſtrooke heere? and the rod of pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtilence drawne out, not onely the bloud and marrow, but the life and ſpirit of many, many thouſands in this Citie? haue not yong &amp; old, mothers and babes, men, and virgins, fainted and fallen downe, before your eyes, both in the corners, &amp; the open places of this place? Hath not the ſtaffe of your bread been broken? Hath there not been blacknes of face, and cleanneſs of teeth in this Citie? London, London, thou pride of nations, and glory of the earth, bleſſe thy God, that there is peace within thy walles, and plentiouſnes within thy pallaces; and that the rod of plague and famine is not ſo much as ſhaken ouer thee; but take heed, leaſt pride, and
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:1204:19"/> fulnes of bread, and the ſins of Sodome, bring not onely a plague of the bodie, and a famine of bread: but a plague of the ſoule, &amp; a famine of the word vpon thy head. <hi>Againe,</hi> hath not the ſame, <hi>occident vos, they ſhall kill you,</hi> beene found here? witnes <hi>Mariana tempora,</hi> that <hi>quin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quennium</hi> of Queene <hi>Mary,</hi> when our Martyrs were made faggots for the fire, and the verie ſtones and pauements of your ſtreets were wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed with their bloud. But Lord God, our hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly, and holy Father, let no ſuch holy father as the <hi>Pope,</hi> no ſuch bloud-ſucker as <hi>Boner,</hi> mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirize and maſſacre againe, in this our Ile; And if there bee any in this land, that wiſh they might, let them haue my wiſh with them, would all their heads ſtood but on one neck, that one faire blow might ſtrike them off; and let all that fauour this my wiſh, ſay Amen.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fourthly, you ſhall be hated for my name:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">S. Mat.</note> And when euer more then now were Chriſts Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles hated and deſpiſed? Are not we held, <hi>om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nium peripſema,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Cor. 4.</note> the very refuſe and of-ſcouring of the people? And as the boyes cried after the Prophet, Come vp thou bald pate, come vp thou bald pate, ſo doth not the world cry after vs, come vp thou Prieſt, come vp thou Prieſt: In the law none that was lame, or deformed, but the choiſeſt of the people were made Prieſts; but now Prieſthood, &amp; Chriſt our high Prieſt is ſo contemned, that if one haue but one defor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:1204:20"/> ſonne, they hold him fit enough to make a Prieſt:<note place="margin">1. Cor. 1.</note> Thus are we made, <hi>purgamenta mundi,</hi> as the filth of the world vnto this day: I ſpeake not this to ſhame you, for though it were the ſhame of Ieruſalem to kill her Prophets, yet it is, and hath euer been your honor of this impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall City, to cheriſh vp the meſſengers of God: yet am I bold to tell you here at home, what fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour we and our calling find abroad.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">S. Matth.</note>
                  <hi>Fiftly, there ſhall bee falſe Prophets, and falſe Chriſts;</hi> and this is verified euen in our daies: For who can be a falſer Chriſt, then the ſonne of perdition Antichriſt? And need wee goe far for falſe Prophets, when the Prophets of Rhemes, and Rome, neſt and ſwarme, I will not ſay onely at Rome, but almoſt in euery roome?</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">S. Mat.</note>
                  <hi>Sixtly, iniquitie ſhall abound, and charitie wax cold:</hi> And alas that our ſin were but greene; and our iniquitie but in the blade; would wee were not growne ripe in ſin, and that wee were not ready for the ſickle: would our offences, like <hi>Nabucodonoſors</hi> tree, were not grown vp to hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, and did not couer the whole land! O that there were but a plenty, and not an exceſſe of ſinning! Oh that, that ſinne of exceſſe did but remaine, and not raigne among vs! But alas our age hath now another deluge, not of wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, but of wine: And though Lucifer lie bound in hell, yet walkes hee looſe and free vpon the carth. Nay more, wee may take vp that of the
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:1204:20"/> Orator, <hi>ferae propria, homo omnia habet vitia;</hi> Beaſts are faultie in ſome things, but men in all things are moſt vitious. <hi>Abundauit iniquitas,</hi> iniquitie hath abounded. And as for charitie, that is not cold, but ded; nay twiſe ded, and pluck'd vp by the root: For men will feede their hawkes, and hounds, and horſes, and that with diet, and with their owne hands; and yet ſuffer poore ſoules, whoſe ſoules were as dearely bought as theirs, to pine and die for want of foode.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Seuenthly, the Goſpel ſhal be preached to al the world:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">S. Matth.</note> And hath not the ſound thereof gone through the earth? Hath not Aſia had her ſeuen churches? Hath not S. <hi>Peter</hi> been the Tutor of the Iew, and S. <hi>Paul</hi> the Doctor of the Gentiles? Did not the Apoſtles, thoſe ſeeds-men of the word, preach the Goſpel to euery creature? And though they call vs, <hi>Et penitus toto diuiſos orbe Britannos,</hi> Brit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines ſet apart from all parts of the world, yet hath the Goſpell ſounded vnto vs; and that ſo lowd, that there is no nooke, nor angle of this Ile, where the language of the goſpel is not heard: And, O Lord, let the light of thy Goſpel ſhine for euer in this our little Goſhen: Let our candle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticke neuer be remoued, not our candle put vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a buſhell: Let not darknes couer this Land, nor groſſe blindneſs our people, but let thy truth, like the Sunne, breake forth dayly more &amp; more, till it come to her full brightnes.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Laſtly,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">S. Matth.</note> 
                  <hi>the abomination of deſolation ſhall bee ſet
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:1204:21"/> vp in the holy place.</hi> And though Rome were once the holy citie; though her faith, as then it was, were famous throughout the world, yet is not the abomination of deſolation ſet vp in hir?<note place="margin">Rom.</note> Looke into the liues of the Popes, and Cardinals, how ſome haue beene idolaters, ſome ſorcerers ſome Sodomites, ſome adulterous, ſome inceſtuous, all, or the moſt, more or leſſe impious, &amp; tell mee where abomination can be, if it be not here? <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kot,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Holkot.</note> one of their own, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſeth, that among them, they who in the morning did worſhip, <hi>virginem matrem,</hi> the bleſſed Virgin-mother, did at night make, <hi>virgines matres,</hi> of maides mothers. O double abomination! Thus you ſee, that theſe eight fore-running ſignes are paſt already, and haue ouerrun vs; and therefore what remaines now,<note place="margin">1. Tim. 4.</note> but a fearefull expectation of iudgement?</p>
               <p>We reade in <hi>Timothy,</hi> that in the laſt daies, <hi>Qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam diſcedent, ſome ſhall depart from the faith: Et quidam transfugae,</hi> and ſome of our runnagates of Rhemes, and Rome, that were in, but not of our church, haue fled to the Popiſh ſinagogue, from our chriſtian Catholique church: but they were, <hi>Quidam,</hi> but certain vncertaine men, that hauing nothing but hope &amp; fortune, to be their guides, would venter vpon any fortune:<note place="margin">S. Bern.</note> ſo that, as S. <hi>Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard</hi> ſpeakes, <hi>deſperatio fecit Monachos,</hi> they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came Mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kiſh not out of iudgment but deſpaire.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> ſaith <hi>Timothy, ſome ſhall attend to the Spirit of errours;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Tim. 4.</note> and our Separiſts of
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:1204:21"/> 
                  <hi>Amſterdam</hi> haue clothed euery naked, and reuiued almoſt euery ded errour: Theſe bee thoſe our Engliſh Phariſees, which will not bee, <hi>ſicut reliqui,</hi> as others; but diuiding them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues from all, they onely will bee the ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar and elected brethren: but to theſe I ſay, that God is the God of vnitie; and that Chriſt was neuer the author of diuiſion.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirdly,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Tim. 4.</note> 
                  <hi>ſome ſhall maintaine doctrine of Diuels:</hi> and doe not the Papiſts while they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny marriage, and allow ſtewes, and ſimple for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication, in the one teach, in the other tolerate a doctrine vnfit for any but a Diuell?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Laſtly,</hi> ſaith <hi>Timothie,</hi> in the laſt dayes,<note place="margin">1. Tim. 4.</note> 
                  <hi>men ſhall haue their conſciences ſeared;</hi> and had wee but windowes in our breaſts, mutually to behold each others conſcience, I feare mee we ſhould ſee, the conſcience of the rich man ſeared with pride: the yong mans conſcience ſeared with wrath: the old mans with auarice: the great mans with vaine-glorie: and all men, both great and ſmall, with ſome greater or leſſe impietie. Thus then as Chriſt our iudge came to fulfill all, ſo wee may conclude, that all, that ſhould come before the comming of Chriſt, is now fulfilled. Therefore I will now ſpeake of that which ſhall follow the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
               <p>Here I obſerue, that there ſhall bee two at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendants and followers of the iudgement, <hi>prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mium,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:1204:22"/> &amp; poena,</hi> reward and ruine: The reward ſhall bee euery way abſolute: <hi>Firſt</hi> in <hi>place,</hi> as being in Heauen, not on Earth: <hi>Secondly</hi> in <hi>continuance,</hi> as beeing not for time, but for euer: <hi>Thirdly,</hi> in <hi>eſſence,</hi> as being not in body onely, or in ſoule onely, but in ſoule and bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die. In the bodie glorified and rewarded ſhall bee (as the Schoole obſerues) foure things.<note place="margin">Thomas.</note> 
                  <hi>Firſt, claritas,</hi> beautie and clearenes: inſomuch that Saint <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">S. <hi>Chryſoſtome.</hi>
                  </note> that the bodies of the Saints ſhall be, <hi>ſepties clariora ſole,</hi> ſeuen times brighter then the Sunne. <hi>Secondly,</hi> in bodies glorified, there ſhall be ſpirituall <hi>agili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie;</hi> and hence it is that ſome aſcribe, the acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uitie and quicknes of our <hi>ſoule,</hi> and <hi>ſpirit,</hi> to a glorifide <hi>bodie;</hi> ſaying, that ſuch bodies are not ſpirits, but ſpiritualized bodies. <hi>Thirdly</hi> in a glorifide body there is, <hi>imp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſsibilitie;</hi> for though here wee ſuffer of euery thing, yet there we ſhall be ſubiect to no corruptiue paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion or ſuffering. <hi>Lastly,</hi> there ſhall be in a glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous bodie,<note place="margin">S. <hi>Auguſt.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>immortality;</hi> here indeed, <hi>orimur, &amp; morimur,</hi> at our birth we begin to die; <hi>acce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dimus,</hi> we enter into the world: <hi>ſuccedimus,</hi> we ſucceed one another in the world: and at laſt, <hi>decedimus,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iob.</note> we depart all out of the world: but when wee ſhall ſee God in our bodie, as <hi>Iob</hi> ſpeakes, we ſhall haue immortall bodies.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly</hi> after iudgement there is a reward for the ſoule: and that reward conſiſts princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:1204:22"/> in two things; in our <hi>vnion</hi> with GOD: and our <hi>viſion</hi> of God: both theſe may bee ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered out of that of Saint <hi>Iohn,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">S. Iohn.</note> when he ſhal appeare we ſhall be like vnto him, and ſhall ſee him as he is: we ſhall bee <hi>like vnto him,</hi> there is our <hi>vnion;</hi> and ſhall <hi>ſee him</hi> as hee is, there is our <hi>viſion.</hi> Others adde to the beatitude of the ſoule, two other actes; one the <hi>frui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion;</hi> another the eternall <hi>retention</hi> of God. And it is controuers'd among the learned, in which of theſe foure actes, the felicitie of the ſoule doth conſiſt.<note place="margin">Henri. Ganda.</note> 
                  <hi>Henricus Ganda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenſis</hi> thinkes the ſoules happineſſe, reſides, in her <hi>vnion</hi> with GOD, becauſe that <hi>v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion</hi> doth deifie the eſſence of the Soule. <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas</hi> laies it to the <hi>viſion</hi> of the Soule, becauſe,<note place="margin">Aquin.</note> that <hi>viſion</hi> doth bleſſe and beatifie the vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding of the Soule: <hi>Scotus</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Scotus.</note> drawes it to the <hi>fruition</hi> of the Soule, becauſe, that <hi>fruition</hi> doth ſatisfie the will of the Soule:<note place="margin">Aureo.</note> 
                  <hi>Aureolus</hi> puts it to the <hi>retention</hi> of the Soule, becauſe that, and that only, doth fully glad and reioice the Soule. I will not determine: Onely I ſay, bleſſed ſoules and bodies ſhall haue, <hi>trium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phum, &amp; gaudium,</hi> triumph and ioy. They ſhall haue triumph, <hi>firſt,</hi> ouer death, for death ſhall be no more. <hi>Secondly,</hi> ouer him that hath the power of death, that is the Diuell, for they ſhall be freed from his power. Againe they ſhal haue ioy, <hi>firſt</hi> in the Maieſtie of God, <hi>ſecondly</hi>
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:1204:23"/> in the humanity of Chriſt, and <hi>thirdly</hi> in the ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cietie of Angels and Saints.</p>
               <p>There is alſo after iudgement, <hi>poena,</hi> a pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment for wicked ſoules. And this puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is double,<note place="margin">Aquin.</note> 
                  <hi>ſenſus &amp; damni,</hi> of ſenſe, and loſſe: of ſenſe: for there the wanton eye ſhall ſee fearefull obiects: the delicate ſmell feele fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy odors: the dainty eare heare ghaſtly how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings: In ſo much that a good Father breakes out thus, <hi>O ſi,</hi> O that we could lay our eares to the mouth of hell; O that we could heare and ſee what men ſuffer in hell, doubtleſs we would deſcend, <hi>viui ad inferos,</hi> to a liuely conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of hell in this life, that ſo we might eſcape it after this life. For there is a <hi>fire</hi> for the body, and a ſpirituall <hi>worme</hi> for the ſoule, and both theſe eternall. For well were it with the dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, if they might bee no longer in hell, but till a Doue could take vp all the ſand of the ſhore; or a Wren drinke vp all the water of the Sea; or a Child gather all the graſſe of the earth; or a man count all the ſtarres of heauen; for then there might be at length ſome hope of releaſe; but this is <hi>Orcus orci,</hi> the hell of hell, that the wicked muſt reſide for euer in hell. So I come to the order that God will vſe in iudgement, <hi>Quaeret,</hi> hee will queſtion all our wayes and workes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>God will reſolue foure queſtions in the day of iudgement; <hi>Firſt</hi> the queſtion, <hi>An ſit Deus,</hi>
                  <pb n="39" facs="tcp:1204:23"/> againſt the Atheiſt, who ſhall then finde that there is a God: <hi>Secondly,</hi> the queſtion, <hi>Quid ſit Deus,</hi> againſt the Papiſt, who ſhall then ſee, that ſtockes and ſtones are not God: <hi>Thirdly,</hi> the queſtion, <hi>Quotuplex Deus,</hi> againſt the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumers, and deſpairers; for then the preſumer ſhall feele, that God is iuſt, as well as merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full: and the deſpairefull behold, that God is mercifull as well as juſt. <hi>Laſtly,</hi> the queſtion <hi>Propter quid homo,</hi> againſt all the wicked, who ſhall then know; that though God made the world for man, yet hee made man for himſelfe and not the world.</p>
               <p>And in this <hi>Quaere,</hi> and inquiſition of the iudge, though it will extend to all things, yet ſuffer me to obſerue but two things: <hi>Quid, &amp; Quos,</hi> what, and whom God will then viſite and enquire of. <hi>Firſt, Quid,</hi> what will God viſite? Man, and the eſtate of man. Man, to ſee if man remember, whence he was, and had his crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: and whither hee haue not loſt the image of his Creator. God will demand of man, what he was by nature: who hee was in perſon: of what ranke and order hee was in life and conuerſation. Nay God will ſcan, and ſift all that is in man: He wil demand if our wiſedome haue not beene craft: our ſeueritie rigor:<note place="margin">Muſſo.</note> our iuſtice crueltie: and our gouernment tyranny. Hee will aske if our autoritie haue not beene oppreſſion; and our zeale contention: He will
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:1204:24"/> viſite and ſee, if our humblenes haue not been baſenes; and our curteſie haue not beene flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terie, our ieſting ſcurrilitie, our free life diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtie, and our ſilence ſingularitie. He will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand if our ſimplenes were not folly, and our feruor in religion, formall hypocriſie.</p>
               <p>And if we dare conteſt with God, and ſay, <hi>Quid mali?</hi> What euill haue I done? the Lord will aske, <hi>at quid boni,</hi> but haſt thou not left much good vndone? If thou ſay I haue not hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, <hi>alienaa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vitam,</hi> the life of another: he wil aske, <hi>at qutuam,</hi> but how haſt thou ordered thy owne life? If thou ſay, <hi>non blaſphemaui Chriſtum,</hi> I haue not blaſphemed Chriſt, hee will aske, <hi>nonne blaſphemaſti Chriſtianum,</hi> but what, didſt thou neuer ſpeake ill of any Chriſtian? If thou ſay, <hi>Neminem occidi,</hi> I haue kild no man; hee will aske, but haſt thou not hated, &amp; ſo kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led thy brother in thy hart?<note place="margin">S. Luke.</note> If thou ſay I faſt; God will viſite and ſee, whether thou faſt for thy purſe, or for the poore: if thou ſay as did the Phariſee, I giue almes; God will viſite, and ſee if thou haue giuen them for his glorie, or thy owne pride and vaine-glorie.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly</hi> I obſerued, <hi>Quos viſitabit,</hi> whom God will viſite: Indeed God will viſite all ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners: but becauſe a world of time would not ſerue me, to open all the ſinnes of the world, ſuffer me to ſet but three regnant, and praedo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minant ſinnes before you:</p>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:1204:24"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> then God will viſite the <hi>Vſurer:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Theſaur nonus.</note> and if that of the Poſtill be true, this will be a heauy Viſitation for him; For he is a bloudy, a crim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, a ſcarlet ſinner, nay wurſe then any other ſinner: Hee is wurſe then the <hi>thiefe,</hi> for the theefe takes it priuily, and in the night: but the Vſurer takes openly and in the day; nay hee takes both night and day. <hi>Secondly</hi> a Vſurer is wurſe then the <hi>graue,</hi> for the graue reſtor'd hir<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ded at the Paſsion of Chriſt: but hee neuer re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtores, though the poore bee ready to fall into many, and many a bitter paſſion. <hi>Thirdly,</hi> a V<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurer is wurſe then <hi>hell,</hi> for hell tormenteth on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the euill, but hee cruſheth, and oppreſſeth both good and euill. <hi>Fourthly</hi> a Vſurer is wurſe then a <hi>Iew,</hi> for a Iew will not take of a Iew: but a Chriſtian Vſurer will take, and ouer-take a Chriſtian. <hi>Fiftly</hi> a Vſurer is wurſe then <hi>death,</hi> for death kils but the body, but hee pines and kils both body and ſoule. <hi>Sixthly</hi> a Vſurer is wurſe then <hi>Iudas,</hi> for Iudas ſold Chriſt but once, but he buyes and ſels Chriſt, in his Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, euery day. <hi>Laſtly,</hi> the Vſurer is wurſe then any ſinner, for the Glutton will ſometime faſt, the proud man wil ſometime be humble, &amp; euery ſinner, wil ſometime leaue of, &amp; reſt from his deare &amp; darling ſin, but the vſurer wil neuer reſt fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> taking intereſt. Nay more, the houſe of a Vſurer, is the bank of the Diuel; &amp; the purſe of a Vſurer, it is, <hi>Os diaboli,</hi> the mouth of the Diuel.</p>
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:1204:25"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> God will viſite the <hi>Temple-pirate, and the Church-robber:</hi> for he can diſpute from Chriſt againſt the Miniſters of Chriſt: Chriſt ſaith he was poore and naked, and why then do the Miniſters of Chriſt ruffle it in ſilkes, &amp; ſtrut it in their ſattin? Chriſt was a foote man, and neuer rid but to Ieruſalem on an Aſſe, why then are the Miniſters of Chriſt growne ſo gay, that they muſt haue their change and choiſe of horſes? Chriſt had not a place where to lay his head, why then haue the Meſſengers of Chriſt not onely places, but Lordly pallaces? Yea, yea, <hi>hoc vrit homines,</hi> it is this that grieues the harts of ſome, to ſee the Church hold vp her head: not that they ſo malice the Church, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they would alſo incloſe the land of the Church. But tell mee, haue the Legates and Embaſſadors of earthly Kings, and that iuſtly, their honour and place, and ſhall the Legates of the King of heauen, haue no place, no honour? or becauſe the Infant-church nedd not ſo large, ſo faire a garment, ſhall now the church, being in her full growth, goe more then halfe bare and naked? You make your Sonnes and Daughters clothes according to their ſtature, and their growth, and ſhall the Kings Daughter, grow ſhee neuer ſo high, goe alwaies in the ſame attire? No, no, ſince wee giue you ſpirituall things, and that in abundance, you ſhould not pare,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:1204:25"/> nor lop, nor cut off our temporall eſtates.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirdly,</hi> God will viſite the Simoniſt; for he enters into the Church, not by the doore, as Chriſt the head did, but he betrayes Chriſt for money as <hi>Iudas</hi> did: Hee comes,<note place="margin">Theſaur: nouus.</note> 
                  <hi>in locum ſpiritus,</hi> into a ſpirituall place, but it is, <hi>reſpectu carnis,</hi> for ſome carnall reſpect: ſo that hee may be, <hi>collector pecuntae,</hi> well monied: but he can neuer be, <hi>rector animae,</hi> well minded. And heere me thinkes I ſee a couetous patron, that like <hi>Iudas</hi> ſels CHRIST for, <hi>Quid mihi dabitis,</hi> what will you giue me? and a ſacrilegious per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, that thinkes Chriſt can bee bought, with that of the Diuell, <hi>Haec omnia dabo,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">S. Iohn.</note> all this will I giue. We reade in Saint <hi>Iohn,</hi> that Saint <hi>Peter</hi> was, <hi>victus per ancillam,</hi> ouercome of a Maide, and I feare there bee ſome patrons in the world, that will not giue liuings, before they be, <hi>victi pro filiis, &amp; filiabus,</hi> ouercome for the good of their wiues, and children: yet the Prophet <hi>Micha</hi> pronounceth a woe to them,<note place="margin">Micha.</note> 
                  <hi>qui aedificant Sion ſanguinibus,</hi> (I know the ſenſe litterall, but giue me leaue to apply) that giue the goods of Sion and the Church, to thoſe onely of their owne bloud: as if the poſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſeſſion of the Lord went by deſcent, and not deſert. <hi>Viſitabit Deus,</hi> God, the great Biſhop of the whole earth, will viſite for theſe things. So much of the Maieſtie of the <hi>iudge,</hi> &amp; <hi>iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment;</hi> now of the miſerie, and ſtate of thoſe
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:1204:26"/> that muſt ſtand in iudgement: and that ſhall be ſo great, that they ſhall not know, what to doe, or ſay. Firſt, <hi>Quid faciam,</hi> what ſhall I doe?</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p n="1">1 This part of my ſpeech muſt be <hi>reall,</hi> and <hi>perſonall: Reall,</hi> and then what will thoſe doe that make the world, and the things of the world their ſtay,<note place="margin">S. <hi>Bernard.</hi>
                  </note> when the world, <hi>Et res, &amp; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culae mundi,</hi> and all the wealth and ſubſtance of the world muſt paſſe away? What will the penny-father, and couetous perſon doe, who, like the Serpent,<note place="margin">Gen.</note> is euer licking vp the duſt of the earth, and ſcraping vp gold and ſiluer, that <hi>red,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">S. <hi>Bernard.</hi>
                  </note> and <hi>white earth,</hi> when ſiluer and gold, and earth ſhall be no more? What will the proud ones doe, that fold themſelues in ſilkes, and <hi>loade</hi> themſelues with <hi>pearles,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">S. <hi>Hiero.</hi>
                  </note> and <hi>iewels,</hi> when iewels and pearles ſhall be no more? what will the wantons doe that crowne themſelues with buds of Roſes,<note place="margin">Prou.</note> when there ſhall be no budde nor Roſe? What will the bibber doe that wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheth away his ſoule in Wine, when there ſhall bee nor Vine, nor grape? How will the magnificent and ſtately builder doe, when building and ſtate ſhall fall to the ground? What will the grand purchaſer doe, that layes houſe to houſe, and land to land, when he ſhall ſee nor houſe, nor land? In a word, what will any worldling doe, when the world it ſelfe muſt be vndone? when there ſhall be no earth
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:1204:26"/> to beare vs, no skie to pleaſe vs, no fountaines to coole vs, no ſhades to hide vs, no ſunne to warme and light vs, no foule or fiſh, no hearb or beaſt, for to feede vs; no houſes to receiue vs, no Temples or Churches to inſtruct vs: in this Chaos and confuſion of all things, what ioy can there be in any thing?</p>
               <p>And now muſt I turne my topicke place, a <hi>rebus ad perſonas,</hi> from beeing a Reall to be perſonall. <hi>Firſt</hi> therefore (you graue and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerend Iudges,) ſuffer, not me, for who am I, or what is the houſe of my father, that I ſhould ſpeake before you? yet ſuffer my text to ſpeake, not onely to your eares, but to your hearts.</p>
               <p>Then (graue and reuerend Iudges,) you that are the fortreſſes of this Land for ſecuritie; the walles of this land for ſtrength, the flowers of this land for fairenes: <hi>Et faui,</hi> and the hunny-combes of this land for ſweetnes, if you that bee called gods, iudge againſt God: if you iudge not as God doth with <hi>tranquillitie;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Wiſedome.</note> but as the wicked iudge did, for <hi>importunitie:</hi> if you, that be, (as <hi>Hugo</hi> ſpeakes) <hi>homines primi,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Hugo</note> the firſt and chiefeſt men, iudge not your ſelues firſt, before you iudge other men: if in iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, you beate downe,<note place="margin">S. <hi>Auguſt.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>aegrotum potius quam morbum,</hi> rather the offender then the offence: if you be, <hi>iudices quaſi ius dicentes,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Cyprian</note> rather ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers then dooers of the Law: if you that ſit to
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:1204:27"/> condemne ſinne, haue either the ſame, or a greater ſinne: if you bee pricers, <hi>non iuris ſed muneris,</hi> not of the cauſe but of the coine: if you iudge for fauour, or feare, or faction, or af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection; if you delay, or haſten; inuert, or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uert iudgement, here is a <hi>Quid facietis</hi> for you, what will you doe, when God ſhall call you to iudgement, and ſhall viſite, as it is in the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Oſee,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Oſee.</note> the Iudges and their wayes?</p>
               <p>And you the Right Honorable Lord Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ior of this honored and admired Citie, you that are the head the eye, the hand, and heart of this great bodie; if you cut not off the head of ſinne; if you ſtrike it not euen to the heart; if your eye ſpare, and will not finde offenders; or your hand be ſhortned and will not reach them: if you put not to death thoſe dedly ſinnes, which haue too much life in this your Citie: if you be not a father to the Orphane; a righter of the Widdow and the Poore: if you that beare the name, and office, and ſword of God, faint in your office, and protect not with Gods ſword the Name of God: if you doe not iuſtifie, and condemne, thoſe good, and bad, that appeare before you, here is a <hi>Quid facies</hi> for you, what will you doe, when you ſhall appeare before the Lord?</p>
               <p>And you learned Counſellers of the Law, you that are factors for the truth, and the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gents and inſtruments of peace, if you hinder,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:1204:27"/> as it is in <hi>Zacharie,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Zacha.</note> the iudgement of peace and truth: if you kindle debate, and bee as the ſeeds-men of ſedition:<note place="margin">Plutar.</note> if like <hi>Camels</hi> you trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble the water, that you your ſelues may drink the better: if your <hi>Counſels,</hi> infringe Gods <hi>precepts:</hi> if you come ſometime with querkes and trickes of Law, ſometime with color and pretext of conſcience, but to ſubuert both law and conſcience: if you that ſhould plead for right and iuſtice, make iuſtice a ſtranger in hir owne Court, here is a <hi>Quid facietis</hi> for you, what will you doe when you are called to that heauenly Court? Take heed, <hi>periculoſum eſt,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">S. <hi>Ambro.</hi>
                  </note> ſaith Saint <hi>Ambroſe, in foro verſari,</hi> it is great danger to follow Courts: for <hi>Iudas, in foro,</hi> in a Law-Court ſold Chriſt; and <hi>Simon Magus, in foro,</hi> in a Law-Court would haue bought the holy Ghoſt.</p>
               <p>You the holy Miniſters of the holieſt, you that bee the Angels and Embaſſadors of GOD: the ſeruants of the Lord, and the tongue of the LORD vnto his ſeruants; if you haue before your mouth, <hi>non oſtium,</hi> not a doore which may open and ſhut, <hi>ſed obstacu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum,</hi> but a wall which will neuer open; if you affect to ouerſee Chriſts flocke, not as it is, <hi>opus bonum,</hi> a good worke,<note place="margin">1. Tim. 3.</note> but as it may gaine you, <hi>opes &amp; bona,</hi> goods and wealth: if you take the houſes of the Lord in poſſeſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and take no care to build vp the Lords
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:1204:28"/> houſe: if you ſay and doe not: if you bee not like <hi>cockes,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">S. <hi>Greg.</hi>
                  </note> firſt beating downe ſinne in your ſelues, and then crowing out againſt the ſinne of others: if you that be, <hi>ſal terrae,</hi> the ſalt of the earth, looſe your ſauour: if you that bee <hi>ſol mundi,</hi> the light of the world, giue no light, here is a <hi>Quid facietis</hi> for you, what will you doe, when God ſhall bring euery thing to light?</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Eccl.</note>You Gentles, and Gallants of this age, that be in the very pride and glorie of your time, and the May and Floure of your youth, if you remember not, that remember thy <hi>crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor</hi> in the dayes of thy youth, but make your ſelues vaſſals to any, euen the fayreſt <hi>crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture:</hi> if you ſeeke for, not the true glorie of GOD, but the vaine glorie of this vaineſt world: if you deſire rather a gorgeous &amp; rich back, then with true valour, and vertue, to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rich your minde: if you bee hot and feruent ſpirits, and yet more forward for the fleſh, then for the ſpirit, here is a <hi>Quid facietis</hi> for you, what will you doe, when you ſhall bee ſtripped of fleſh and ſpirit?</p>
               <p>You beauteous Ladies; and faire matrons, and damzels of this Honorable Citie, you that are the obiect of euery eye, and perhaps the deſire of many hearts: if you come hither clothed like <hi>Salomon</hi> in his royaltie, rather to draw the eyes, and chaine the hearts of others
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:1204:28"/> vnto you, then to lift vp your owne eyes and hearts vnto your God: if you take more care to powder the haire, and plaiſter the face, then to ſeeke God and his face; if you make the hayre of ded men and women to liue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine vpon your heads: if you make,<note place="margin">Eſay</note> as the Prophet ſpeakes, a tinckling with your feet, and thinke the ground too baſe for you to goe on: if any of you be, (as I hope none is) either like <hi>Semiramis</hi> laſciuious, or like <hi>Cleopatra</hi> proud and ambitious: if like <hi>Thamar</hi> you ſit in the way for to enſnare, or like <hi>Dalila</hi> you offer a bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome but to murther: if like <hi>Herodias</hi> you loue to daunce, and ſtriue, rather to keepe meaſure in your footing, then your liuing: if you more regard a glittering, and gariſh ſuite, then a gracious, and godly ſoule: if you more weigh a light feather, then the Law of your heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Father, here is a <hi>Quid facietis</hi> for you, what will you doe when you ſhall be excluded from God your Father? And if, as aſhamed of Gods image, and ſcorning that forme and face which hee hath lent you, you picture and paint out to your ſelues annointed faces; ſuffer, not mee, but Saint <hi>Ambroſe</hi> to tell you,<note place="margin">S. <hi>Ambroſe.</hi>
                  </note> that this daw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing and parjetting of the face, is in ſome reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect wurſe then adulterie it ſelfe: For in that foule act, <hi>perſona vitiatur,</hi> onely the perſon is polluted; but in this vngodly and vnnaturall painting, <hi>natura laeditur,</hi> euen nature her ſelfe is
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:1204:29"/> more then too much corrupted.</p>
               <p>To ſumme vp all in a word: you who like <hi>Abſalon</hi> ſtand faire, yet bee ambitious: you who like <hi>Achab</hi> be rich and yet be couetous: you that like <hi>Achitophel</hi> be wiſe and yet maliti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous. You Marchants that venter more for gold, then for God: you artizans in generall, that loue more the gaining of a noble, or a crowne, then you feare the loſſe of a heauenly and eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall crowne, here is a <hi>Quid facietis</hi> for you all, what will you doe, when you ſhall ſtand before the iudge of all?</p>
               <p n="2">2 <hi>Secondly,</hi> we ſhall not know what to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere: <hi>Quid reſpondebo?</hi> What <hi>ſhall</hi> I anſwere? It is in the ſingular, what <hi>ſhall</hi> I anſwer, to ſhew that God will ſingle out, and ſet apart euerie one to anſwere for himſelfe. In this iudgement we cannot anſwere by a proxie, a deputie, a ſollicitor, or atturney; nay the Kings of the earth, cannot ſend their Vice-royes, and Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gates, to anſwere for them, before the King of Heauen. For God will ſend out his atach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and as it were his <hi>ſub poenâ,</hi> to make euery one appeare, either to paine, or reſt, in his owne perſon. Let vs then follow that coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell which <hi>Moſes</hi> gaue vnto the Hebrew, <hi>at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tende tibi,</hi> looke vnto thy ſelfe, ſince euerie man muſt anſwere for himſelfe. Let vs remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber that,<note place="margin">S. Matth. 9.</note> of Chriſt in the Goſpel, <hi>vade in do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum tuam,</hi> goe into thy owne houſe: the houſe
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:1204:29"/> of thy familie; the houſe of thy bodie; the houſe of thy ſoule; and the houſe of thy con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience which is kept within thy ſoule; for eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie man muſt anſwere, for the order, or diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of his owne houſe. And, <hi>domus tua,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Muſſo.</note> 
                  <hi>ipſe tu,</hi> man himſelfe is the houſe of man. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if the head of this houſe rebell, it muſt ſubmit: if the eyes, thoſe windowes of this houſe be vaine, they muſt be ſhut: if the ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, thoſe doores and gates of this houſe bee looſe, they muſt be kept: if the fleſh, the wall of this houſe be weake, it muſt, by being more weakned in the outward man, bee made ſtron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger to Chriſt, who is God and Man. And if any part of this houſe bee out of order, wee muſt labour to order it, and that well, and in euery part.<note place="margin">Eſay 38.</note> Elſe when it ſhall bee ſaid to thee, as it was to <hi>Ezekias,</hi> thou ſhalt die, what wilt thou anſwere to the liuing God, in that iudgement which muſt follow after death?</p>
               <p>What will the hypocrite anſwere then, who doth now couer, <hi>Luciferum ſuum,</hi> his pride vnder the mantle of humilitie, when after death hee ſhall haue no part in Chriſt, that humbled himſelfe vnto the death? what will the blaſphemer anſwere then, who now comes too neere vnto God with his lips, and ſweares him ouer, from head to foot, part after part, when in the ſweet mercies of his God,
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:1204:30"/> hee cannot haue the leaſt part? What will the furious ſpirits, and vnmanly manhood anſwere then, who now count it their greateſt grace, to mangle and murther a man, for a lie, or a leſſe diſgrace, and cannot ſtay till they waſh their hands in bloud, when they ſhall bee bard the benefit and bleſſing of Chriſt, and his moſt precious bloud?</p>
               <p>In this ſtrict Viſitation of the Lord, the malitious cannot anſwere, wee are men, and cannot forgiue our enemies: for they ſhall ſee Saint <hi>Steuen</hi> a man,<note place="margin">Acts</note> not onely pardoning, but praying for his enemies. In this viſitation the deuouring gluttons, who doe nothing but feaſt, and ryot, cannot ſay wee were men and could not faſt: for they ſhall ſee <hi>Iohn Baptiſt</hi> a man,<note place="margin">S. <hi>Hierome.</hi>
                  </note> whoſe life was a <hi>perpetuall faſt.</hi> What then ſhall wee anſwere? Wilt thou ſay with Saint <hi>Paul, nihil ſum conſcius,</hi> I know nothing againſt my ſelfe: alas thou canſt not. For as Saint <hi>Iames</hi> ſpeakes,<note place="margin">S. Iames.</note> in many things we offend all: yet if thou couldſt, this will not acquit thee, this will not iuſtifie. Better were it with the Publicane to <hi>ſtand farre off,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">S. Luke.</note> as knowing thy filthineſſe: <hi>to looke on the ground,</hi> as confeſſing thy vnworthineſſe; <hi>to knocke thy breſt,</hi> as ſhewing thy penſiuenes; to cry, <hi>miſerere,</hi> Lord haue mercie, as being guiltie: and that, <hi>on me a ſinner,</hi> as beeing laden with miſerie. Or wilt thou anſwere with Saint <hi>Peter. Non noui homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem,</hi>
                  <pb n="53" facs="tcp:1204:30"/> I know not the man; when euer did I ſee Chriſt hungry, and did not feede him? or na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, and did not cloth him? alas good Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, Chriſt himſelfe will reply thus againſt this anſwere; inaſmuch as you haue not fedde the hungry Chriſtian, you haue not fed Chriſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in that you haue not clothed the naked Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, you haue not clothed me: as then in him you haue not knowne me, ſo now, <hi>Neſcio vos,</hi> I know you not, you ſhall not raigne with me? And here, like him in the Goſpel, that wanted his wedding garment, wee muſt needes ſtand ſpeechleſſe: and no maruell. For if we be not able to anſwere <hi>ſicknes,</hi> when it ſpeakes vnto vs, how then ſhall wee anſwere, <hi>ſaluti nostrae,</hi> that iudge, that Ieſus, who is the Lord both of ſicknes and health? If wee bee not able to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere <hi>death,</hi> when it ſhall queſtion, and arreſt vs, how then ſhall we anſwere the God both of life and death?</p>
               <p>But what? wilt thou flie from anſwere to pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition? and come with a <hi>ſupplicat</hi> to the iudge? Why in this dreadfull iudgement, and day of miſerie, there is no place left for mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie: yet doth a good father, bring in thus, a ſinner, and his iudge; ſweet Sauiour (ſaith the ſinner) remember now thy bitter paſſion: true (ſaith the iudge) but yet now there is nor time, nor place for co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>paſſion: yet Ieſus, let me come vnto thee: no, for in thy life thou ſaidſt,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:1204:31"/> Depart thou maiſt not come neere vnto mee. Yet Ieſus haſt thou but one bleſſing, giue me a bleſſing before I part: no, thou art vnder the curſe of the Law, and therefore goe from mee you curſed. Yet ſince wee are accurſed, let vs feele, no other puniſhment, then thy curſes: Yes, as you haue burnt with the fire of luſt, ſo goe you curſed into the fire: ah, but who is able to endure this flame: Let it not ſweet Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus continue long: yes, as you would haue ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned for euer, ſo ſhall this fire laſt for euer, Go into euerlaſting fire. Yet giue vs ſome com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable mates and fellowes, which may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſh vs in this flame: no, but as you were of your father the Diuell, ſo goe into that flame, which was prepared for the Diuell.</p>
               <p>What now ſhall a ſoule thus ſurprized doe? whither ſhall it flye? from Chriſt vnto Chriſt: from Chriſt as hee will bee our iudge, vnto Chriſt as hee is yet our Ieſus. It is a terme a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong thoſe that be graduates in the ſchoole, <hi>Reſpondebit pro me Ariſtoteles,</hi> that <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> the eye of nature, and heart of Philoſophie, ſhall anſwere for them: ſo wee that are blanke and dumbe of our ſelues, haue no other an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chor of hope but this, <hi>Reſpondebit pro nobis Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus,</hi> that Ieſus our bleſſed Sauior will intercede, and mediate for vs. And ſweete Ieſus let thy wiſedome anſwere for our folly: thy humilitie for our pride: thy meeknes for our cruelty: thy
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:1204:31"/> righteouſnes for our ſinne: Thou, O Ieſus, art a lambe without any ſpot, anſwere thou for vs, who like Iacobs Lambes are full of ſpots. And if God bleſſed <hi>Laban</hi> for <hi>Iacobs</hi> ſake, much more will hee giue vs a bleſſing for Ieſus ſake:<note place="margin">Gen.</note> 
                  <hi>Oſtende patri latus &amp; vulnera,</hi> Preſent, ſweet Ieſus, to thy Father, thy ſide,<note place="margin">S. <hi>Bernard.</hi>
                  </note> that as thy ſide was opened, ſo his heart may be open vnto vs: preſent alſo thy bleeding wounds, that thoſe wounds may heale vs, from thoſe ſinnes, that like the bloud of <hi>Abel</hi> cry againſt vs. So I come to ſpeake in a word, of the laſt word of my text, anſwere <hi>him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3 We are but, <hi>vermiculi,</hi> little wormes that crawle and creepe on the face of the earth, and what can we anſwere him, who is Lord both of heauen &amp; earth? We are but, <hi>vernaculae,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">S. <hi>Bernard.</hi>
                  </note> the vaſſals and ſlaues of ſinne, and what can wee anſwere him, who in heauen, earth, and hell: angels, men, and diuels, hath puniſhed, and will puniſh ſin? The heauens melt, the moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines ſmoke, the earth quakes, and the Che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rubins couer their faces from him, and the foure and twenty Elders caſt downe their crownes before him, <hi>Et quid coenum coelo,</hi> O then how ſhall we euer be able to anſwere him? He is goodnes it ſelfe, and we are euill: hee is wiſedome it ſelfe, and wee are fooliſh: hee is powre it ſelfe, and wee are weake: <hi>non ſumus reſpondendo,</hi> we cannot be able to anſwere him.
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:1204:32"/> For if that readie Philoſopher were daunted and ſilenced at the ſight of <hi>Hannibal,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Plut.</note> and his manly preſence:<note place="margin">Dan.</note> if the Prophet <hi>Daniel</hi> were diſmaied at the view of an Angell: how will the approch of him, who is the God both of Angell and Man, daunt, and diſmay vs? When Chriſt came into the world to <hi>ſaue</hi> his people, yet then thoſe that came to take him, fell down before him: how then will hee, as it were, fell and hew downe ſinners, when he ſhall come to <hi>iudge</hi> his people? In the Reuelation, <hi>dilectus iudicis, Iohn</hi> the Diſciple whom Ieſus loued, fell on his face,<note place="margin">Reuel.</note> 
                  <hi>viſione iudicis,</hi> when hee ſaw his iudge but in a viſion: how great then will be the fall of thoſe that loue not God, when they ſhall both ſee, and feele him, in his moſt rigorous and ſeuereſt action?<note place="margin">Cyprian.</note> Saint <hi>Cyprian</hi> is ſaid ſo much to feare, <hi>diem iudicii,</hi> the day of iudgement, that he cleane forgate, <hi>diem Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirii,</hi> the day of his martyrdome and earthly torment: and no maruell neither, for, <hi>timor mortis, nihil ad timorem iudicis,</hi> the feare of a temporall death, is nothing to the feare of him, that hath power of eternall life and death. And if they be in ſuch a maze, <hi>ad quos iudex,</hi> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to whom, and for whoſe glorie the iudge ſhall come: how then will they ſtand amazed, <hi>contra quos iudex,</hi> againſt whom, and for whoſe eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall ſhame, and paine the iudge ſhall come?</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>But becauſe my houres are ſpent, and I am
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:1204:32"/> not as <hi>Ioſua</hi> was, able to ſtay the Sunne, I will but <hi>perore</hi> of the Iudgement in a word, and ſo commit you to him that muſt bee our iudge, euen our God. You haue heard, <hi>firſt,</hi> of the <hi>day,</hi> &amp; <hi>time</hi> of iudgment, how though ſome would haue it in the day, ſome in the night, ſome at <hi>midnight,</hi> ſome in one, ſome in another, <hi>watch</hi> of the night, yet <hi>latet dies &amp; hora,</hi> that day and houre is not knowne, that wee might expect it euery houre both of day and night.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> you heard that God ſhould iudge; and then, ſince many were called Gods, that, <hi>Deus vniuerſi,</hi> the GOD of the whole world ſhould iudge the world: and <hi>thirdly,</hi> that ſince in this one God there were three perſons that God the Father had committed the iudgment to his Sonne, the ſecond perſon: and <hi>fourth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> ſince in this ſecond perſon, there were two natures, a diuine, a humane nature, you heard, that hee ſhould iudge <hi>humanum genus,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">S. <hi>Auguſt.</hi>
                  </note> all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinde in his humanitie: otherwiſe <hi>periret hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manum genus, ſi iudex non eſſet humanus,</hi> all men of euery kinde, might periſh, if the iudge ſhould not be humane and kinde.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirdly,</hi> you heard of the comming of this iudge; and therein two things: <hi>Firſt,</hi> the <hi>cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taintie</hi> of his comming; and that in reſpect of GOD, in reſpect of Man, in reſpect of Chriſt, who is God and Man. <hi>Secondly</hi> the <hi>vicinitie</hi> of his comming, <hi>non inſlat ſed extat iudicium,</hi>
                  <pb n="58" facs="tcp:1204:33"/> the iudgement is not neere, but euen ſo neere, that now is the iudgement of this world.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fourthly,</hi> you heard of the iudgement it ſelfe; and there <hi>firſt</hi> the <hi>multiplicitie</hi> of iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; <hi>ſecondly,</hi> the <hi>qualitie</hi> of this iudgement; <hi>thirdly,</hi> the <hi>forerunners;</hi> and <hi>lastly,</hi> the <hi>followers</hi> of this iudgement.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Laſtly,</hi> in the iudgement, you heard of the order by which God would proceed; it was, <hi>quaerendo, viſitando,</hi> he will demaund, aske, and viſite; and there I obſerued two things, <hi>Quid,</hi> what hee would demaund; <hi>Et quos,</hi> and who they were that he would viſite.</p>
               <p>In thoſe that muſt bee iudged, I noted three things; <hi>Firſt</hi> they ſhall not know <hi>what to doe: ſecondly</hi> they ſhal not know <hi>what to anſwere:</hi> and <hi>thirdly,</hi> ſince they haue ſinned againſt <hi>him</hi> that muſt bee their iudge, they ſhall not know what to anſwere <hi>him:</hi> For the ſummes of our ſinnes are great, and we cannot croſſe or cancell the hand-writing which is againſt vs; and therfore, bleſſed Ieſus, naile this hand-writing vnto thy croſſe; and the more thou ſeeſt our miſeries to be, ſo much the more remember that we need thy great mercie. It was thy pleaſure to weepe ouer <hi>Lazarus:</hi> and ſweet Ieſus, let it pleaſe thee, to giue vnto vs, <hi>gratiam lacrimarum,</hi> true peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentiall teares, to waſh our ſores, that are poore Lazares ouer-ſpred with ſinne. Vnto <hi>Lazarus</hi> thou ſaideſt, <hi>veni foras, Lazarus</hi> come forth; ſo
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:1204:33"/> vouchſafe, deere Ieſus, to ſay to vs, and call vs forth of that ſinne, wherein wee lye ſtinking, like rottennes, corruption, and the graue. <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid</hi> profeſſed, that he was, <hi>mundus a ſanguine,</hi> free and cleare from the bloud of <hi>Abner:</hi> but, gracious Ieſus, let vs be, <hi>mundi per ſanguinem,</hi> clenſed &amp; purged by thy moſt precious bloud.<note place="margin">S <hi>Auguſt.</hi>
                  </note> For we haue no other refuge, but to flie, <hi>ab ira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to deo, ad placatum,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Reuel.</note> from Chriſt as hee ſhall bee our iudge to Chriſt as he is yet our Ieſus: <hi>Veni domine Ieſu,</hi> Come Lord Ieſus; come quickly: Yet come, not as a rigorous iudge to condemn vs: but come as a Sauiour and a Ieſus to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaſe vs. Now to this Ieſus, the Sonne of God, with the Father and the holy Ghoſt, bee aſcribed all honour, power, praiſe, and Maieſtie, now and for euer.</p>
               <closer>Amen.</closer>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>Errata.</head>
            <p>For not, read <hi>non.</hi> pag. 9. lin. 22. for then, read <hi>thence. p.</hi> 17. lin. 6. for Separiſts, <hi>Separatists.</hi> pag. 34. <hi>l. the laſte,</hi> for alienaam, <hi>alienam</hi> p 40. l. 11. &amp; <hi>at quî tuam?</hi> p. 40. l. 12. for curſes, r. <hi>curſe</hi> p. 54. l. 7.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
